Inventory of the Russkiĭ Katolicheskiĭ TSentr
Hoover Institution Archives
Russkii Katolicheskii TSentr
1906-1975
86026
24 manuscript boxes (9.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reminiscences, letters, studies, bulletins, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to Russian military operations during World War I; White Russian military operations during the Russian Civil War, especially in Siberia; political and economic conditions in the Soviet Union; and Russian émigré activities in the United States and elsewhere. Collected by the Russkiĭ Katolicheskiĭ TSentr in San Francisco.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
What was the Russkii Katolicheskii TSentr in San Francisco is now Our Lady of Fatima Byzantine Catholic Church, an Eastern-Rite Catholic parish grounded in the Russian tradition. At some point in the 1960s the center began collecting books and manuscript materials with the idea of becoming a cultural and politico-religious institute. The center eventually chose not to pursue this line of development and transferred to Hoover the material in this collection.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reminiscences, letters, studies, bulletins, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to Russian military operations during World War I; White Russian military operations during the Russian Civil War, especially in Siberia; political and economic conditions in the Soviet Union; and Russian émigré activities in the United States and elsewhere. Collected by the Russkiĭ Katolicheskiĭ TSentr in San Francisco.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Eastern Front.; Russia. Armiia.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russia--(Territory under White armies, 1918-1920)--Armiia.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russians--United States.; Russkiĭ Katolicheskiĭ TSentr (San Francisco, Calif.)
Collection Contents
- BORIS B. FILIMONOV FILE, 1917-1961 (Box 1-5)
  Correspondence, financial records, maps, photographs, writings, and other material authored and collected by B. Filimonov. Arranged by physical form
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1919-1928 (Folder 1: 1)
      - 1929-1934 (Folder 1: 2)
      - 1935-1936 (Folder 1: 3)
      - 1936-1940 (Folder 1: 4)
      - 1940 (Folder 1: 5)
      - 1940-1942 (Folder 1: 6)
      - 1942-1947 (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1947-1948 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1949-1961 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Diterikhs, M., 1924 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Financial records, 1925-1927 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Maps, annotated, undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - Photographs, 1917 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Writings
    - General, undated (Folder 2: 8, Folder 3: 1-2)
    - "Belyia armii vostochnogo fronta,", undated (Folder 3: 3)
    - "Konnye narvtsy," Shanghai, undated (Folder 3: 4-5)
    - "Krasnoufimtsy - 1918 god,", undated (Folder 3: 6)
      Includes research materials
    - "Voennye deistviia,", undated (Folder 3: 7)
    - "Bor'ba v Zaural'e, 1918," Shanghai, 1935 (Folder 4: 1)
    - "Put gonimykh,", 1936 (Folder 4: 2)
    - "Vospominaniia o sluzhbe v 68-oi pekhotnoi divizii Komandira 271-go pekhotnogo polka, Polkovnika Stepana Ivanovicha Bruevicha," Shanghai, 1941 (Folder 4: 3)
    - "Novorzhevtsy," Shanghai, 1930-1947
      - Correspondence, notes, copies of documents, 1930-1943 (Folder 4: 4-6)
      - Typescript, 1947 (Folder 4: 7, Folder 5: 1-6, Folder 6: 1-2)
    - "Novorzhevtsy," Shanghai, 1949 (Folder 6: 3)
- WRITINGS BY VARIOUS AUTHORS, 1939-1967 (Box 6-7)
  Correspondence, drafts, essays, manuscripts, and notes of various authors. Arranged alphabetically by name of author
  - Liukov, Vladimir A., undated (Folder 6: 4)
    Drafts and notes relating to his military career as an officer in the Russian Imperial army during World War I
  - Mikhailov, D. M., "Vospominaniia, 1918,", undated (Folder 6: 5)
  - Musii-Musienko, I. V., Russkoe khristoliubivoe voinstvo, Shanghai, 1939 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Skriabin, A., "Mirnoe I boevoe proshloe L.Gv. Konno-Grenaderskago polka," Tom VI, Paris, 1967 (Folder 6: 7-8)
  - Zambrzhitskii, A. V., "Germano-sovetskaia voina, 1941-1945," New York, 1954 (Folder 7: 1)
- RUSSIANS IN FOREIGN COUNTRIES FILE, 1915-1977 (Box 7-15)
  Clippings, printed matter, serials/newspapers, and other material concerning Russian emigre individuals and organizations. Arranged by physical form
  - General
    - Bologov, Grigorii K., 1952 (Folder 7: 2)
    - China. Obhshchestvennyi Sovet Russkoi Kontsesii v Khan'kou, 1915-1924 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Efimoff, Alex, 1942 (Folder 7: 4)
      Biographical material and photographs
    - Efimov, Avenir, 1924-1951 (Folder 7: 5)
      Correspondence and writings
    - Far Eastern Society, San Francisco, 1974-1975 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Obshchestvo gallipoliitsev, 1939 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Orthodox Church of America, Archdiocese of San Francisco, 1943 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia
      - General, 1938-1973 (Folder 7: 9)
      - Archdiocese of San Francisco, 1933-1967 (Folder 8: 1-2)
    - Russkii obshche-voinskii soiuz v Marokko, 1952 (Folder 8: 3)
    - San Francisco (California)
      - Convent of Our Lady of Vladimir, 1960 (Folder 8: 4)
      - Obshchee Kadetskoe Ob'edinenie, 1958 (Folder 8: 5)
      - Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi Voiny, 1959 (Folder 8: 6)
      - Russian Center, 1940-1974 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Soiuz rossiiskikh kadetskikh korpusov, Paris, 1924-1961 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Clippings, 1932-1970 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Printed matter
    - General, 1929-1976 (Folder 9: 1-4)
    - Berezin, T. A., Russkii iazyk, istoricheskie sud'by i iazyk i idei A. S. Pushkina (New York), 1937 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Bez zabrala, sud boshii, Angliia i eia politika, undated (Folder 9: 6)
    - Builleten' Obshchestva Russkikh Inzhenerov i Tekhnikov (San Francisco), N. 1, 1929 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Biulleten' osvoboditel'nogo dvizheniia narodov Rossii
      - No. 2 (25), 1949 (Folder 9: 8)
      - No. 2 (13), 1950 (Folder 10: 1)
    - Biulleten' Tsentral'nogo Komiteta po sboru sredstv v kaznu Velikogo Kniazia (New York), 1957 July (Folder 10: 2)
    - Biulleten' Ukranskogo Vizvol'nogo Rukhu (Munich), 1951-1953 (Folder 10: 3)
    - Derzhavnaia Rus', undated (Folder 10: 4)
    - Dmitriev, V., K teorii natsional'noi revoliutsii, undated (Folder 10: 5)
    - "Dnevnik Barona Alekseia Budberga," Arkhiv russkoi revoliutsii, Volume XII, 1918 (Folder 10: 6)
    - Dolg chesti (San Francisco), odnodnevnyi zhurnal k invalidnomu balu
      - 1934 October 27 (Folder 10: 7)
      - 1937 (Folder 10: 8)
      - 1960 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Dukhovnoe probuzhdenie (Helsinki), No. 12, 1955 (Folder 10: 10)
    - Eliseev, Polkovnik, V khram voiskovoi slavy (New York), 1957 (Folder 10: 11)
    - Informatsionnyi biulleten' (San Francisco), No. 4, 1955 (Folder 10: 12)
    - Informatsionnyi biulleten' otdela Obshchestva Gallipoliitsev v S.Sh. (New York), 1970 December - 1971 November (Folder 10: 13)
    - Informatsionnyi biulleten' rukovodiashchego tsentra Obshcherossiiskogo Monarkhicheskogo Fronta (New York), No. 25-No. 33, 1968 (June)- 1971 (December) (Folder 10: 14)
    - Informatsionnyi biulleten' za prava is svobodu v Rossii (Frankfurt)
      - No. 2, 1957 (Folder 10: 15)
      - No. 3, 1958 (Folder 10: 16)
      - Nos. 7-8, 1958 (Folder 10: 17)
    - Informatsionnyi listok (Ontario), Soiuz Bor'by za Osvobozhdenie Narodov Rossii, No. 145, 1976 (Folder 10: 18)
    - Informatsionnyi listok Soiuza Bor'by za Osvobozhdenie Narodov Rossii (Ontario), No. 147, 1977 (Folder 10: 19)
    - Iubileinyi biulleten' Soiuza Russkikh Belykh Voennykh Invalidov v Argentine (Buenos Aires), No. 6, 1959 (Folder 10: 20)
    - Iuzno-Kaliforniiskii otdel Zarubezhnogo Soiuza Russkikh Voennykh Invalidov (Los Angeles), 1951 February (Folder 10: 21)
    - Izvestiia Vysshago Monarkhicheskogo Soveta (Dornstadt)
      - No. 12, 1955 (Folder 10: 22)
      - No. 14 (Folder 10: 23)
      - Nos. 15-17, 1956 (Folder 10: 24)
    - Izvestiia Vysshago Monarkhicheskogo Soveta (Munich), No. 177 (October), 1948 (Folder 10: 25)
    - Kashin, A., Sovetsko-kitaiskie otnosheniia (Munich), 1961 (Folder 10: 26)
    - Kitai (Shanghai), 1923 (Folder 10: 27)
    - Korpusnik (New York), 1970-1971 (Folder 10: 28)
    - Kratkaia istoriia Soiuza Russkikh Voennykh Invalidov v Shankhae (Shanghai), 1936 (Folder 10: 29)
    - Ledianov pokhod, 1949 (Folder 10: 30)
    - Lektsii o Rossii, undated (Folder 11: 1)
    - Lopukhin, P. S., Sviataia rus' i russkoe gosudarstvo, 1953 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Lukianov, E. V., Novye metody montazha shnurovoi provodki elektricheskogo osveshcheniia (Moscow), 1953 (Folder 11: 3)
    - Man'chzhurskii okhotnik i rybolov (Harbin), 1934 (Folder 11: 4)
    - Nerushimaia tverdyniia (Shanghai), 1938 (Folder 11: 5)
    - Obshchestvo "Spasem Rossiiu,", undated (Folder 11: 6)
    - Osvedomitel'noe pis'mo (Buenos Aires), Pravlenie Obshche-Kadetskogo Ob'edineniia v Argentine, No. 9, 1957 (Folder 11: 7)
    - Osvedomitel'nyi listok Russkago Obshche-Voinskago Soiuza (Brussels), No. 3, 1951 (Folder 11: 8)
    - Osvobozhdenie (Munich), No. 2, 1951 (Folder 11: 9)
    - Pamiatka o bor'be Izhevtsev i Votkintsev s bo'shevikami v 1918-1922 godakh, undated (Folder 11: 10)
    - Pod belym krestom, No. 1, 1951 (Folder 11: 11)
    - Pomoshch bedniaku (Harbin), undated (Folder 11: 12)
    - "Predskazanie o derzhave rossiiskoi," Nasha strana (San Francisco), No. 43, 1959 (Folder 11: 13)
    - Protokol obshchago sobraniia Obshchestva Byvshykh Russkikh Morskikh Ofitserov v Amerike (Association of Former Russian Naval Officers in America)
      - 1945-1958 (Folder 11: 14)
      - 1950-1954 (Folder 11: 15)
      - 1955-1960 (Folder 12: 1)
      - 1961-1964 (Folder 12: 2)
    - Put' (Hamburg), No. 10 (98), 1948 (Folder 12: 3)
    - Rossiiskii grazhdanin russkii klich (Arolsen/Wadeck, Germany), 1950 November-December (Folder 12: 4)
    - Russkie v Kalifornii (San Francisco), 1935 (Folder 12: 5)
    - Sbornik materialov o vydache kazakov v Lientse i drugikh mestakh v 1945
      - Orangeburg, New York, 1956 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Vypusk 16, 1958 (Folder 12: 7)
    - Sbornik rossiiskoi voennoi poezii (Paris), 1957-1961 (Folder 12: 8)
    - Semenovskii biulleten' (San Francisco), November-December 1950 (Folder 12: 9)
    - Soiuz Bor'by za Osvodozhdenie Narodov Rossii - 8-oi s'ezd, 1977 (Folder 12: 10)
    - Stanichnik (Melbourne, Australia), No. 2, 1966 (Folder 12: 11)
    - Ustav Narodno-Trudovogo Soiuza, 1957 (Folder 12: 12)
    - Ustav Soiuza Bor'by za Osvobozhdenie Narodov Rossii (New York), 1952 (Folder 12: 13)
    - Vchera, segodnia, zavtra (Munich), 1957 (Folder 12: 14)
    - Vechnaia Rossiia (New York), undated (Folder 12: 15)
    - Vestnik Obshchestva Russkikh Veteranov Velikoi Voiny v San Frantsisko (San Francisco), 1964 March (Folder 12: 16)
    - Vestnik Soiuza Russkikh Pisatelei i Zhurnalistov v Bel'gii (Brussels), 1957 March (Folder 12: 17)
    - Vestnik vtorogo otdela Rossiiskogo Imperskogo Soiuza, undated (Folder 12: 18)
    - Voennyi sbornik (Paris), Nos. 1-2, 1963 (Folder 12: 19)
    - Volny iz Ispanii (Madrid), tetrad' 16, undated (Folder 13: 1)
    - Za moral'nuiu revoliutsiiu, undated (Folder 13: 2)
    - Za vashu i nashu svobodu, Biulleten' No. 1, 1965 (Folder 13: 3)
    - Zapiski Russkago Istoricheskago Obshchestva v Amerike (San Francisco), 1938 October (Folder 13: 4)
    - Zarubezhnyi Soiuz Russkikh Voennykh Invalidov (Paris), 1938 (Folder 13: 5)
    - Zveno (Paris), Nos. 1-2, 1973 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Serials/Newspapers
    - General, 1915-1976 (Folder 13: 7)
    - Aksioma (Buenos Aires), Nos. 1-3, 1952 (Folder 13: 8)
    - Artillerskii zhurnal (Paris), No. 8/9, 1930 (Folder 13: 9)
    - Bote der Freiheit, 1957
      - No. 9 (Folder 13: 10)
      - No. 10 (Folder 13: 11)
    - Budni (San Francisco), 1938 October-1939 March (Folder 13: 12)
    - Dalnevostochnyi vrachebnyi vestnik (Shanghai), No. 1, 1932 (Folder 13: 13)
    - Delo (San Francisco), No. 1, 1951 (Folder 13: 14)
    - Epokha (North Adelaide, Australia), 1973 May/June (Folder 13: 15)
    - Golos zarubezh'ia (Munich), No. 2, 1976 (Folder 13: 16)
    - Gridushchaia Rossiia (Mukden), No. 8, 1932 (Folder 13: 17)
    - Gridushchaia Rossiia (Shanghai), No. 6/7, 1933 (Folder 13: 18)
    - Iunker slushai (Shreveport, Louisiana), No. 1, 1967 (Folder 13: 19)
    - Iuzhnyi krest (Buenos Aires), No. 1, 1951 (Folder 13: 20)
    - Kaliforniiskii al'manakh (San Francisco), 1934 (Folder 13: 21)
    - Kazachii istoricheskii sbornik (Paris), No. 2, 1955 (Folder 13: 22)
    - Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha (San Francisco)
      - No. 2, 1956 (Folder 14: 1)
      - No. 4, 1956 (Folder 14: 2)
      - No. 5, 1958 (Folder 14: 3)
    - Kitaiskii blagovestnik (Beijing), July/August 1939 (Folder 14: 4)
    - Los Angeles R Club Messenger (Los Angeles), Nos. 1-5, 1948 (Folder 14: 5)
    - Maiak (San Francisco), No. 2, 1957 (Folder 14: 6)
    - Nash put' (Bridgeport, Connecticut), Nos. 1-3, 1963 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Nasha oborona (New York), No. 1, 1942 (Folder 14: 8)
    - Nashe obshchee delo (Munich)
      - Nos. 18-22, 1961 (Folder 14: 9)
      - Nos. 2-8, 1964 (Folder 14: 10)
    - Natsiia (Shanghai), No. 10/11, 1934 (Folder 14: 11)
    - Petrushka, United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, No. 1, 1946 (Folder 14: 12)
    - Pokhod (Shanghai), "Otvet A. F. Grushina P. N. Krasnovu,", 1939 January (Folder 14: 13)
    - Politekhnik (Sydney, Australia), No. 2, 1970 (Folder 14: 14)
    - Pravda soldata, No. 10 (33), 1957 (Folder 14: 15)
    - Rus' (New York), No. 5, 1952 (Folder 14: 16)
    - Rus' (Paris), No. 2, undated (Folder 14: 17)
    - Russkaia Pravda, No. 11, 1944 (Folder 14: 18)
    - Russkaia Pravda (Melbourne), No. 7, 1967, No. 2, 1968 (Folder 14: 19)
    - Russkaia rech' (Paris), No. 3, 1958 (Folder 14: 20)
    - Russkie novosti (Paris)
      - No. 969, 1963 (Folder 14: 21)
      - No. 1273, 1970 (Folder 14: 22)
    - Russkii amerikanets (New York), No. 2, 1974 (Folder 14: 23)
    - Russkii golos (New York), 1976 January 15 (Folder 14: 24)
    - Russkii sokol (Austria), No. 1, 1949 (Folder 14: 25)
    - Russkoe slovo (Buenos Aires), No. 291, No. 388, 1965 and 1969 (Folder 14: 26)
    - S narodom - za narod (Munich), Nos. 4-5, 1964-1965 (Folder 14: 27)
    - Slovo (San Francisco), No. 1, 1967 (Folder 15: 1)
    - Svobodnyi Kavkaz (Munich), No. 10 (13), 1952 October (Folder 15: 2)
    - Tainy khollivudskogo dvora (Hollywood), No. 1, 1949 (Folder 15: 3)
    - Vernost? (Philadelphia), 1949 January-June (Folder 15: 4)
    - Vestnik (Paris), Nos. 155-158, 1967-1968 (Folder 15: 5)
    - Vestnik ego vozvrashcheniia (Frankfurt), No. 1, 1965; No. 1, 1967 (Folder 15: 6)
    - Vestnik natsional?nago dvizheniia (Vladivostok), Nos. 2-21, 1922 (Folder 15: 7)
    - Vlasovets (Munich), Nos. 5-7, 1951-1952 (Folder 15: 8)
    - Voennyi vestnik (New York), No. 6, 1955 August (Folder 15: 9)
    - Voskresenie (Esslingen), No. 38, No. 63, 1961-1964 (Folder 15: 10)
    - Voskresenie (Shanghai), No. 1, 1929 (Folder 15: 11)
    - Voskresenie (Stuttgart), Nos. 57-61, 1963 (Folder 15: 12)
    - Vrachebnoe obozrenie (Berlin), No. 7/8, 1928 (Folder 15: 13)
    - Za chest? rodiny, Nos. 27-28, 1949 (Folder 15: 14)
    - Za otechestvo (Montreal), No. 1, 1968 (Folder 15: 15)
    - Za pravdu i svobodu v Rossii (Frankfurt), Nos. 7-9, 1958 (Folder 15: 16)
    - Za svobodu (New York), No. 6/7, 1942 (Folder 15: 17)
    - Zapiski Obshchestva Russkikh Zarubezhnykh Iuristov (Munich), No. 1, 1949 (Folder 15: 18)
    - Zaria (Munich), 1954 April (Folder 15: 19)
    - Zaria svobody (Munich), 1958 May-June (Folder 15: 20)
    - Zhizn' (New York), No. 7, 1925 (Folder 15: 21)
    - Miscellany, 1924-1973 (Folder 15: 22-23)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1985 (Box 16-17)
  Writings, serials, newspapers, printed matter, correspondence, and miscellaneous materials relating to a variety of subjects. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Anticommunism, 1956-1968 (Folder 16: 1)
  - Daubikhe River Valley -- List of populated areas, undated (Folder 16: 2)
  - Institut izucheniia problem voiny i mira, Paris, 1938 (Folder 16: 3)
  - Nicholas II, 1951 (Folder 16: 4)
  - Russia
    - General, undated (Folder 16: 5)
    - History -- Revolution, 1918-1922 (Folder 16: 6-7)
  - Soviet Union
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 16: 8-9, Folder 17: 1-2)
      - 1957-1958 (Folder 17: 3)
      - Landowsky, J., Red Symphony (London), 1968 (Folder 17: 4)
  - Ukraine, 1919-1985 (Folder 17: 5)
  - World War (1914-1918), 1914-1919 (Folder 17: 16)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 18-24)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu